<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ knocking at the doore, or, The substance of a sermon intended to be preached in Pauls upon the Sabbath day which fell upon the fifteenth day of April last: but not preached, by reason of a suddain obstruction of that liberty which was promised him, being indeed unworthy to be the servant of Jesus Christ in any such ministration for ever. / Published by the authour Philip Tanny commonly Tandy.</title>
            <author>Tanny, Philip.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94505</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T149</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1485_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867687</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867687</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170022</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94505)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170022)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 190:E1485[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ knocking at the doore, or, The substance of a sermon intended to be preached in Pauls upon the Sabbath day which fell upon the fifteenth day of April last: but not preached, by reason of a suddain obstruction of that liberty which was promised him, being indeed unworthy to be the servant of Jesus Christ in any such ministration for ever. / Published by the authour Philip Tanny commonly Tandy.</title>
                  <author>Tanny, Philip.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. and are to be sold by Giles Calvert at the Black Spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls, and Simon Miller at the signe of the Starre.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "may 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation III, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170022:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRIST KNOCKING AT THE DOORE, OR, The Subſtance of a SERMON Intended to be Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in PAULS upon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day which fell upon the Fifteenth Day of <hi>April</hi> laſt: But not Preached, by reaſon of a ſuddain Obſtruction of that Liberty which was promiſed him, being indeed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be the Servant of Jeſus Chriſt in any ſuch miniſtration for ever.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by the Authour PHILIP TANNY <hi>commonly</hi> TANDY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.M.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black Spread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> and <hi>Simon Miller</hi> at the Signe of the Starre. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170022:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170022:2"/>
            <head>To his Highneſſe OLIVER Lord Protector of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Highneſs:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now almoſt nine years, ſince I appeared in a Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, except once only at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-ſtone,</hi> where, I thank God, through his bleſſing, I did not wholy loſe my labour.</p>
            <p>I did endeavour before that to have preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> upon a Sabbath day in the afternoon, in D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Burgeſs</hi> his ſubſtitutes room; but he being ſurpriſed on a ſudden, with ſome ſtrange relations touching me, (wherein it may pleaſe God at length to vindicate me, to the ſhame of all my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,) (for I account my profeſſed friends, by reaſon of their injurious actions towards
<pb facs="tcp:170022:3"/>me little leſſe,) on a ſudden; when I came with intention to goe into the Pulpit, to deliver the ſubſtance of what is herewith printed, with ſome enlargements, as my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſhould have dictated; I was to the wonder, I think of many, I am ſure of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, who came to hear me with honeſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, I doubt not, denied the liberty which was very civily promiſed me.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Highneſs, I thank God I can ſay truly (and my heart and conſcience bears me witneſſe to my own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity in ſaying ſo) that I can be content to become a ſpectacle to God, Angels and men, ſince he hath been pleaſed moſt ſtrangely and unexpectedly, to finde out a way to ſhew compaſſion to ſuch a ſinner as I am: of which I was ſo hopeleſſe for a long time together (though I must confeſſe at the beginning of my deſpair, I received the greateſt ſupport by your Highneſſe speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me, that ever I had from any man living,) that I muſt needs ſay, that for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, if not full out nine years together, I never clearly hoped for the reconciled face of a loving God againe: For this reaſon, I ſay once again, I can be content, through the goodneſs of God, to become a ſpectacle to
<pb facs="tcp:170022:3"/>God, Angels and men for Jeſus Chriſts ſake, who I truſt hath had mercy on my ſoul, and hath pardoned my tranſgreſſions, there having been never ſuch a ſinner in the world as I have been. Such a compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion being ſhewed to ſuch a ſinner, the like I ſay again, was never yet in the world, it hath begotten in me a ſuitable, and I hope I may ſay, a Chriſtianlike reſolution, to paſſe by ſuch wrongs and injurious tranſactions uſed towards me, as I may truly affirm, that, all circumſtances conſidered, there were yet never the like of them in the world done to any private man, in a peaceable government: God continue this govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon your Highneſs ſhoulders, and make them ſtrong for their ſervice, which is very great, nay greater then you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of, if I know any thing of God, or of Jeſus Chriſt aright.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why I have troubled the Preſs with my affectionate meditations, upon the action of Chriſt knocking at the doores of our hearts for the entertaining of his mercies, is, becauſe</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> By this I ſhall revive in my memory the many tranſactions which Chriſt in his patience hath uſed toward my ſelf, and
<pb facs="tcp:170022:4"/>be humbled for my own diſobedience and rebellion.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That it might appear to all, that I am no ſower of ſedition, there being nothing more affectionately springing in my ſoul, then my longing deſire to ſee this poor Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein I was born, and have lived (I thank God honeſtly towards man, though ſinfully towards God) the larger half of my days (in humane reaſon,) ſetled and eſtabliſhed in truth righteouſnes and peace.</p>
            <p>I put truth firſt, for if our intellectuals be not better principled touching many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences that are amongſt us, I am certain we cannot be ſtabliſhed in righteouſneſſe, and if we be not ſtabliſhed in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; I am as ſure and certaine, that we cannot be ſtabliſhed in any true and truly comfortable peace.</p>
            <p>I am not without hope, notwithſtanding all difficulties, yet to ſee ſuch a peace. And indeed to ſpeak truth, one reaſon of my hope is, that I ſee generally in all mens expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo little hope of it. For, do not mens hearts ſay within themſelves, How can theſe things be? ſhall a Nation be born in a day? It may be it will; for when the Lord returns the captivity of his people, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:170022:4"/>they not be like them that dreame? Who knows what a day may bring forth?</p>
            <p>We have long looked for a day generally heretofore, but of late men have laboured in the very fire, and yet expected no good, but to live, and not to be ſlaves. Bear up yet a little longer, O <hi>England,</hi> it may be thy Saviour will yet pity thy longings; thou ſeeſt no help, 'tis the more likely, that help is nigh at hand: me thinks I ſee a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, which though appearing but like the palme of a hand, may yet increaſe to a great cloud, which ſhall overſpread the heavens, and bring forth rain to refreſh the earth.</p>
            <p>In this Expectation I do with much comfort of heart aſſure my Soul, your Highneſſe hath a great part to act, a great Stage to act upon, you know not how large: Be pleaſed to look to your ſtation in Jeſus Chriſt ſtrongly and ſuddenly, if your feet ſhall be fixt upon that rock, and your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſtabliſhed in him, this Nation will have reaſon to bleſſe God for you, but if your Highneſs falter too much, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with fleſh and bloud too long, if your affections to Jeſus Chriſt and his poor ones cool, or grow indifferent, or that you look
<pb facs="tcp:170022:5"/>too much upon principles of Policy, which are an Aegyptian Reed, and will deceive you, and all the Princes in the world. You may expect a ſudden hand of Gods venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and diſpleaſure, that ſhall overturn your Counſels, and bring them to fooliſhnes, and God ſhall bring deliverance another way, and reſtore comforts to his Mourners by another hand. I beſeech your Highneſs pardon my plain dealing, I dare not but ſpeak the things which in ſome little mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure I ſee. I have ſpoken herein words of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſſe and honeſt affection to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to this Nation wherein I live; God Almighty give you underſtanding in all things, which concern the publike and your private peace. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſs moſt truly affectionate, and thankefully humble Servant. <hi>PHILIP TANNY</hi> vulgò <hi>TANDY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170022:5"/>
            <head>CHRIST KNOCKING AT THE DOORE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REV. 3. Ver. 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold I ſtand at the doore and knock.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we take this whole Booke of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> and looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it in a more generall view, it ſeemes to me to conſiſt of theſe grand parts: Firſt, Of ſeverall Exhortations, full of life, which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> received from Chriſt the author of them. Secondly, Of certaine high and heavenly predictions, which repreſented to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> the ſtate of the Church till the end of the world. The Exhortations are ſet down in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> and 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Chapters: The predictions from thence to the end. Which he concludes ſo ſweetly, as if he knew not whether he were out of the body or in the body; witneſſe thoſe words of raviſhment, <hi>Rev.</hi> ult. ver. 18. <hi>And the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170022:6"/>ſpirit and the bride ſay come, and let him that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſay come, and let him that is athirſt come, and whoſoever will let him take of the water of life free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> And thoſe other gracious words <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>He which teſtifieth of theſe things ſaith, ſurely I come quickly, Amen: even ſo come Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the firſt Chapter, I looke upon it as containing principally three things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Title of the whole Booke in the three firſt verſes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Preface or Dedication of the whole Booke in the three next verſes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A ſolemne and majeſtical deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jeſus Chriſt the Author of the whole Booke, which I finde ſomething ſcattered in divers parts of the Chapter.</p>
            <p>This deſcription ſeems to be in 4. fragments.</p>
            <p>One is ſet forth by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</p>
            <p>A ſecond is aimed at in the terribleneſſe of his coming to judgement, <hi>ver.</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the third comes to us in the words of Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>ver</hi> 8, 11, 10.</p>
            <p>A fourth is preſented to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> in a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and in that viſion to us; if we have eyes eyes to ſee and eares to heare: from <hi>v.</hi> 13. to <hi>v.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>This viſion was ſo full of amazing majeſty, that when S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> ſaw it, he fell at Chriſts feet, but Chriſt ſoone layes his right hand upon him, and revives him, ſaying unto him, <hi>I am the firſt and the laſt, I am he that liveth and was dead, and behold I am alive for evermore, and have the keyes of hell and of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170022:6"/>
            <p>This viſion being over, and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> having got to himſelfe againe, Chriſt gives him dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to write:
<list>
                  <item>1. The things which he had ſeene.</item>
                  <item>2. The things which are.</item>
                  <item>3. The things which muſt be hereafter.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>That is, as <hi>Pareus</hi> in effects obſerves,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Tranſactions which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> himſelfe had been witneſſe of from the firſt preaching of the Goſpel after Chriſts aſcenfion, till the time of <hi>Domitian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Things, which at the time of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Johns</hi> writing were then on foot.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Things which from thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhould come to paſſe till the end of the world.</p>
            <p>But whether ſome other tranſactions touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the condition of the Church before Chriſt, were not withall aimed at in ſome of thoſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which were repreſented to S. <hi>John,</hi> and are mentioned in this Booke of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> I muſt confeſſe I am yet to learne.</p>
            <p>But to cloſe as faſt as I can. You ſee the maine body of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> branched by me into Exhortations and Predictions, or rather Repreſentations.</p>
            <p>My Text you ſee falls out to be part of the Exhortations, being part of the third Chapter, which concludes them.</p>
            <p>Theſe Exhortations are inſcribed to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Angels of ſeverall Churches. Touching which let me give you one note of <hi>Pareus, Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum non ad ſolos Epiſcopes,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſed ad ipſas quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Eccleſias spect are Epiſtolas, ex Epilog is intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170022:7"/>
            <p>But from the Concluſions its evident, that theſe Epiſtles (I have called them Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) doe not onely belong to the Biſhops, but alſo to the very Churches themſelves: for each Epiſtle ends thus, <hi>He that hath an care to heare, let him heare what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what are the names or diſtinctions of theſe Churches, to whoſe Angels or Biſhops theſe Exhortations are inſcribed? I will barely name them and haſte to my Text.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the Church in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Ch. 2. v. 1.</p>
            <p>The ſecond the Church in <hi>Smyrna,</hi> Ch 2 v. 8.</p>
            <p>The third the Church in <hi>Pergamus,</hi> Ch. 2. v. 12.</p>
            <p>The fourth the Church in <hi>Thyatira,</hi> Ch. 2. v. 18.</p>
            <p>The fifth the Church in <hi>Sardis,</hi> Ch. 3. v. 1.</p>
            <p>The fixth the Church of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> Ch. 3. v. 7.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh and laſt the Church of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceans;</hi> or as the margin of the great Bible hath it, in <hi>Laodieca,</hi> Ch. 3. v. 14.</p>
            <p>I might give you a note here, that the Churches are called Churches in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in <hi>Smyrna,</hi> in <hi>Pergamus,</hi> in <hi>Tbyatira,</hi> in <hi>Sardis,</hi> in <hi>Philadelphia;</hi> nor would any objection croſſe me in the tendency of my note, that the laſt Church is called the Church of <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> or in <hi>Laodicea,</hi> but I promiſed you the naming of the Churches onely, and therefore I preſſe not my note, but haſte according to my promiſe.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170022:7"/>
            <p>At length you ſee plainely and methodically, that my Text is part of thoſe Exhortations or Epiſtles which were directed by Jeſus Chriſt to the Church of the <hi>Laodiceans.</hi> Which if M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Brightman</hi> obſerve aright, in making it a type of our Church here in <hi>England,</hi> it muſt be granted that we are the more concerned to hear what the Spirit of Chriſt ſaith unto this Church; let me cite his note, which having lately ſeen in his Latine edition onely, I think I may give you the ſenſe of them in engliſh thus: <q>But why doth he ſay that he ſtands at the doore and knocks? Why doth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe open the doore? Why doth he not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly enter in? eſpecially ſeeing he hath the key of <hi>David,</hi> by which he openeth nor doth any ſhut, as <hi>v.</hi> 7.</q> And then he adds: <q>Theſe things, ſaith he, are moſt ſignificantly ſpoken, <hi>pro ratione Laodicenſis noſtraeque Eccleſiae,</hi> with a ſutableneſſe to the <hi>Laodiceans</hi> and our Church in which Chriſt ſtands before the doores, but our hearing (ſaith he) is in a manner quite ſtopped or intercluded.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I will not diſpute here whether the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt intended the Church of the <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceans</hi> to be a type of the Church in <hi>England</hi> or not; But be it as it will, this both you and I and all of us in <hi>England</hi> muſt yeeld him, that the reproofs and accuſations faſtened upon this Church, are as fit to be ſpoken and charged upon us as upon any Church this day in the world.</p>
            <p>Let us take the words as they lie in our way, what more true then that Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170022:8"/>knows our works? that we are neither hot nor cold? and ſo becauſe we are lukewarm, how juſtly may we fear, yea, fear and tremble that Jeſus Chriſt will ſpue us out of his mouth, if ever we were in it? for we are generally ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked that it may be queſtioned. How juſtly may Chriſt charge us as the <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> that we ſay, <hi>We are rich, and encreaſed with goods, and have need of nothing, and know not that we are wretched and miſcrable, and poor, and blinde, and naked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How fit are we in ſome ſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> in reſpect of our condition, for that heavenly and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all counſell of Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 18? <hi>I counſell thee to buy of me gold tried in the fire, that thou maiſt be rich, and white raiment, that thou maiſt be cloathed, and that the ſhame of thy nakedneſſe doc not appeare, and annoint thine eyes with eye ſalve, that thou maiſt ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being ſuch ſinners, ſuch lukewarme profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, how ſuitable is it, that we ſhould be put in minde of afflictions, and of the chaſtenings of the Lord, eſpecially if he ſhall be pleaſed to rebuke and chaſten us in love.</p>
            <p>To conclude: How exactly ſeaſonable and agreeable is the exhortation to repentance im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before my Text, <hi>be zealous therefore and repent?</hi> How doth the fire of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his late judgements of fire, conſpire as it were to ſet on this Exhortation to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? but if Jeſus Chriſt doe not ſet it on too by his own powerfull ſpirit, all is to no purpoſe. But for this end, I hope we ſhall finde Jeſus Chriſt knocking at the doores of our ſoules, as heretofore he did at the hearts of the <hi>Laodice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170022:8"/>and happy are we if we heare him knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and open our doore; for if any man heare his voice and open his doore, Chriſt will come in to him and will ſup with him and he with Chriſt. <hi>Behold I ſtand at the doore and knock,</hi> this is my Text, and you ſee how I am come to it, be pleaſed to obſerve in it:</p>
            <p>Firſt, A note of preparation, Behold.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A declaration of an action which Chriſt did to this Church of the <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> he ſtood at their doores and knocked.</p>
            <p>The note of preparation fixeth us upon two Conſiderations:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the thing which followes after it, is worth the marking, and therefore Mr. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons</hi> calls it a note of Attention. <hi>Pareus</hi> to the like purpoſe ſaith thus; <hi>Ecce ex: itantis particula, pulſat aures &amp; corda ut dict is attendant;</hi> This behold, ſaith he, is a particle of ſtirring up, it forcibly ſtrikes upon the eares and heart, that they ſhould attend to thoſe things that are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: both agree in one, that the words of Chriſt here ſpoken, werr diligently to be head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> for they were written to them: and that they are diligently to be heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us likewiſe, for I ſuppoſe we take it for granted, that they are written for our inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Oh then let's heare him, let's heare him; pity it is we ſhould turne the deafe care upon him for ever: we have refuſed him enough al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, have we not? aske your owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, commune with your owne hearts upon the point and be ſtill, and I am confident they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170022:9"/>muſt ſay, they will ſay, we have, we have refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him enough, but ſhall we refuſe him ſtill? is that fit? is it reaſonable? What? ſhall we keepe Jeſus Chriſt out of doores, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps his head be fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led with dew, and his locks with the drops of the night; ſhall we let him knock till his heels ake, as we ſay? nay till his heart ake? rill his provocations ariſe to ſuch a height that he will be gone and leave us; hath Chriſt deſerved this of our ſoules? or doe our ſoules ſtand in no more need of Chriſt, then thus to ſerve him, thus to ſet him packing, with a conſtruction of unkindeneſſe, that we would not ſo much as open doores to him? Doth this ſound well, or will it ſound well in our eares, to be charged with this at the day of judgement? Is it well for Chriſt, or well for us, or well for any, but particularly is it well for our Children, that we ſhould be ſo diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, ſo gainſaying, ſo mad? not well for Chriſt ſure; for what friend can but take it unkindly to be ſo dealt with? Not well for us neither, for being ſo dealt with, what can we expect, but that Chriſt being thus denied, thus refuſed, thus driven away, as I may ſay, he ſhould reſolve to doe with us, ſince the times of the Goſpel, as God did in the old Teſtament, before the times of the Law, <hi>My spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with man?</hi> In a word, what can we looke for, but that he ſhould call no more, knock no more, waite no more? and then may we not juſtly ſay unto our ſouls? Woe unto us for we have exceedingly ſinned.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt was dealt unkindely with by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170022:9"/>the Spouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. (Conſider the paſſage and you will ſee how nearly it concerneth us) you will finde what pains it coſt the Spouſe before ſhe and her Beloved met again. At the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> verſe we finde <hi>ſhe ſleepeth but my heart awaketh;</hi> ſaith ſhe, that's well, her awaking heart heard the voice of her Beloved, <hi>It is the voice of my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that knocks, ſaying, Open to me my Siſter, my Love, my Dove, my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled;</hi> Oh how ſweet are theſe words! how heavenly theſe tranſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions! how raviſhing are theſe paſſages to ſuch as underſtand them and the loving kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Jeſus Chriſt in them; Well, Chriſt doth not only knock and call, and it may be theſe or ſuch like were the words which Jeſus Chriſt uſed to the Church of the <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> notwithſtanding their wickedneſſe, (and indeed I am apt to think ſo by an inclination of my ſpirit, which ſeems rationally to leade me this way, and that is the reaſon, that whenſoever I ſhall have ended my Sermons upon this Text, I ſhall follow them with theſe words of Chriſt in this 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Cant.</hi> v. 2. and the middle part on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and then return to this 3<hi rend="sup">•</hi> of <hi>Revelations,</hi> and the reſidue of this 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>verſe</hi>) But this by the way. To return where I was, Jeſus Chriſt doth not only knock and call as I ſaid, for he would fain come in, but he reaſons the caſe, and pleads for entrance, <hi>Open, open, my Beloved, for my head is filled with dew, and my locks with the drops of the night,</hi> as much as if Jeſus Chriſt ſhould have ſpoken in other words thus, Pray thee my Spouſe, my Love, my Siſter, my Unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, my Dove, my Delight, my any thing, my
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170022:10"/>every thing that is delectable and ſweet to me, Pray thee open door, thou little thinkeſt what pains I have taken to come to thee to night; Alas, I am wet, I do not ſay all over, but my head is filled with dew, and my locks are full likewiſe of the drops of the night, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not, but I may catch cold with thy ſtaying; Open quickly, my dear ſweet friend, my Siſter, my Love, if thou loveſt me that am thy hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, open and let me ſtay no longer: Well, you ſee the plea, but doth it prevail, a man would think it ſhould, 'tis ſtrange it ſhould not, but it doth not; The Spouſe reaſons Chriſt away, and in reaſoning him away reaſons her ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſorrow, as you may ſee by what follows: Jeſus Chriſt being dealt unkindely with with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws himſelf, and it gone, the Spouſe then gets up when 'twas too late, it ſeems that he had pleaded ſo long that ſhe was juſt riſing as I may ſay, when he was going; It ſeems likewiſe that directly at parting he ſpake a word for a farewell that pierced her to the very heart and ſoul, it may be 'twas no more then in one word, Farewell, or I am gone, I will ſtay no longer, you uſe me courſly, unkindely, as if you loved me not: What ere the words were 'tis ſure they ſtung, for ſhe ſaith expreſly, her ſoul failed when he ſpake; Well, but what follows, ſad work, Chriſt knows and your ſouls know too, if you have any acquaintance with Chriſt, I ſought him but I could not finde him, I called him but he gave me no anſwer, No! what? Chriſt give no anſwer when a poor afflicted ſoul cals, that's ſad, my brethren, but thank
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170022:10"/>your ſelves for it, he cals oft, and you will not anſwer him, and therefore it is but juſt with him, that when ye call he likewiſe ſhould not anſwer you; 'twas ſo with the Spouſe and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h been ſo with us, if we have any experimentall knowledge of Chriſt as a Beloved. The Spouſe under this tranſaction findes things go ſadly with her, afflictions come tumbling on her like waves one upon the neck of another, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no wonder ſeeing Chriſt is gone, <hi>Woe unto you when I depart from you.</hi> But ſee how ſhe is put to it, ſhe hunts after her Beloved when he was gone, ſhe now ſeeth 'twas better riſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; as ſhe hunts and ſeeks about, ſhe lights upon the watch and the watch upon her, ſhe was catched abroad at unſeaſonable hours, after midnight belike, it may be about four of the Clock in the morning, but how did the Watch ſerve her? they ſmote her, and the blows were no ſmall ones, we uſe not to ſtrike children ſo; 'tis ſaid they wounded her, nay, it ſhould ſeem they left her dead, elſe 'tis like they would have carried her to priſon, but by them ſhe is left belike, and then ſhe fals into worſe hands, at leaſt not better, for the Keepers of the Walls light upon her, and they take away her Veil; Beaten, Wounded, Rob'd, you ſee ſhe is, this was great affliction, hard uſage, but all this is nothing to the loſſe of her Beloved; 't was he, 'twas he that was gone that had withdrawn himſelf, her ſoul failed when ſhe ſpake, for him ſhe is ſick, ſick at heart, ſick of love; and I tell you my Brethren and Siſters, love-ſickneſſe is heavy ſickneſſe, What ſickneſſe like it? 'Tis
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170022:11"/>an affliction greater then beating, wounding, robbing, eſpecially if ſpiritual, the Spouſe tels you that plainly, for though beaten, wounded, rob'd, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ob'd by thoſe that ſhould have comforted her, yet all her complaint ſeems to be, that her Beloved was gone, that he had withdrawn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that ſhe could not finde him, and therefore being wearied with ſearching, ſhe ſeems to ſit her down, panting under her affliction, and as if ſhe were able to do no more, ſhe cries out to the <hi>Daughters of Jeruſalem,</hi> (by which I think you may underſtand ſuch afflicted ſouls as are beginning to look after Chriſt, and being young do groan like little young children after him) To theſe I ſay ſhe cries out, (as being moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably likely to tell her ſome news of Chriſt, becauſe of his tenderneſſe to ſuch ſouls, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perpetually ready to ſuccour them) And how doth ſhe cry out to them? truly ſhe ſpeaks as if ſhe were now fainting, and could do no more for her ſelf; <hi>I charge you O ye Daughters of Jeruſalem, that if ſhe finde my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ye tell him I am ſick of Love;</hi> And what think ye now (my ſweet Friends) is it good ſlieghting of Chriſt? Is it good refuſing of him? Doth the Sppuſe think ſo? No. And What can you think ſo that have heard this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment? Take need, Take heed, my Brethren, what ye do; You ſee what it coſt her, you know not what it may coſt you, if you deal unkinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him; If ye refuſe to hearken and to yeeld up your affections as well as your ears to the words which he ſpeaks, what know you whether he will ſpeak again for ever? You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170022:11"/>ſay abſolutely, but that the ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt may be ſpeaking to you in me now, at this very time, ſeaſon, and moment, I ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whoſe I am, God in due time will bear me witneſſe, and bear witneſſe with me, if I am his; Fly not like the moth too buſily about the Candle of your own Conſciences; If you ſlieght the burning light of that Candle, yet conſider betime, that 'tis too great a boldneſs, to play and dally with the Spirit of God, who is a conſuming fire: Oh <hi>kiſſe the Soune leſt he be angry,</hi> if he be angry, yea but a little, <hi>bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi> For Gods ſake, for Chriſts ſake, for the Converſion of Souls ſake, for your Childrens ſake, methinks theſe concernments ſhould have ſome prevalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with you; By all theſe, and all the mercies of God, if ever Chriſt knocks, deal but as civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him as generally we do with ſtrangers, ask him, Who's at doore? he will anſwer you doubtleſſe, 'Tis I, 'Tis I, Pray you open and let me come in, for this he knocks, calls, cries. But what will he do when he comes in? He will do any thing that is good for us, he will ſweep the houſe, clenſe our hearts, waſh away our ſins, waſh our garments, or clothe us at leaſt with clean white linnen; Theſe things done, he will make ready a Feaſt for us, a <hi>Feaſt of fat things,</hi> and when all is ready he will ſit down with us, <hi>he will ſup with us,</hi> nay, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ſup with us too, he with him, both with us, we with them; Come, Come, my hearts, I am again your Petitioner, for Chriſts ſake, for your Souls ſake, for your Childrens
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170022:12"/>ſakes, little do you think how much they are concerned in the account of your yeelding; yeeld, yeeld, great hearts, throw down the bars, away with your oppoſitions, your luſts, your ſins; Let me break open doors at this time with thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 24.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Lift up your heads, O ye gates, and be ye lift up, ye everlaſting doors, and the King of glory ſhall come in. Who is the King of glory? the Lord ſtrong and mighty, the Lord mighty in battell. Lift up your heads, O ye gates, even lift them up, ye everlaſting doors, and the King of glory ſhall come in. Who is this King of glory? the Lord of Hoſts he is this King of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the word <hi>Behold,</hi> as 'tis a note of Attention, but I told you it ſixeth us upon two Conſiderations; and the ſecond Conſideration is point of Admiration, I muſt ſay ſomething of that too.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Behold</hi> is often uſed in ſuch a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of ſignification; <hi>Behold a virgin ſhall conceive with childe. I</hi> need not quote Texts for that which is ſo obvious; it is a note of Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and let it be granted ſo to be here, for ſurely 'tis matter of admiration, that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould ſtand at the doores of ſuch a wicked people, ſuch ungodly, hypocriticall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors as this Church of the <hi>Laodiceans</hi> was, we are: but behold he doth it, though it be a ſtrange thing for us to patterne ſuch a patience, yet 'tis not a ſtrange thing for Chriſt to ſet us ſuch a copy: <hi>this is the Lords doing, and 'tis mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous in our eyes,</hi> that he is ſo good, ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſo patient, ſo that we muſt needs looke a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170022:12"/>little upon this word <hi>Behold</hi> in this ſenſe of wonder; and truely wonderfull it is, if either you conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who it is that declares himſelfe, 'tis <hi>I,</hi> ſaith Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What he declares himſelfe to doe, he ſtands, <hi>Non dicit venio, ſed sto,</hi> ſaith an honeſt Expoſitor, He doth not ſay, I come, and I ſit, but <hi>I ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But where ſtands he; looke and wonder I beſeech you, he ſtands <hi>at the doore, Cur non aperit,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Brightman,</hi> Why doth he not open the doores? nay, <hi>Cur non effringat fores?</hi> Why doth he not breake open doores? ſay I, he can if he will, but he doth not, but there he ſtands.</p>
            <p>But is the doore open? no: the more wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked they, we, all, 'tis ſhut, yet he will not be gone, for my Text ſaith, he ſeeks for entrance fairely, he knocks.</p>
            <p>He knocks ſaith my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ext: but if you looke into the following words in this very ſame verſe, you ſhall finde he calls too; for 'tis ſaid. <hi>If any man heare my voice, and open the doore,</hi> &amp;c. Surely a voice, a call, could not be heard, nor ſuppoſed to be heard, unleſſe there were a call, unleſſe there were a voice, both then muſt be yeelded; he knockt, he calld, he did ſo to them, it may be he doth ſo to us: Let me onely put you in minde, before I come to cloſer exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that it may be we ſhall finde this true, that <hi>pulſando vocat, &amp; vocando pulſat, imo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum effringit fores:</hi> that by knocking he calls, and by calling he knocks, nay at length breakes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170022:13"/>open the doores. You know what Chriſt ſaith to this purpoſe, if we rightly underſtand it, <hi>The houre is come, and now is, when the dead ſhall heare the voice of the Sonne of man, and thoſe that heare ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt point of Admiration, lyes in the Conſideration of the party who declares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, 'tis I, <hi>Behold I ſtand at the doore and knock.</hi> I, Who is that? <hi>ver.</hi> 14. tells us,</p>
            <p>Ver. 14. <hi>Theſe things ſaith the Amen, the ſaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and true witneſſe, the beginning of the creation of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is called <hi>the Amen;</hi> in the Greeke 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ille</hi> Amen, that Amen: and who is that Amen? the next words tell us, <hi>'tis the faithfull and true witneſſe.</hi> And who is this fairhfull and true witneſſe? let the Scripture tell you plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Grace be unto you, and peace from him who is, and was, and is to come, and from the ſeven ſpirits whih are before his throne, and from Jeſus Chriſt, who is the faithfull witneſſe,</hi> deſcribed after to be him <hi>that loved us, and hath waſhed us from our ſinnes by his owne bloud. Anſelme</hi> hath a very uſefull note upon this very word, <hi>quia dicturus erat (ſcilicet Chriſtus) rem mirabilem. quod tepidi excommunicandi &amp; de ore ſuo projici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi eſſent, qui ab hominibus boni credebantur (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>audi nec tamen eſſent) ideo promittit ſe veracem eſſe, &amp; ut in his fibi credendum eſſe videatur, ideo dicitur ille Amen,</hi> or to this purpoſe, and very neere theſe words, Becauſe, ſaith he, Jeſus Chriſt was to ſpeake of a wonderfull thing, <hi>viz.</hi> that lukewarme perſons were to be excommunicated by Chriſt, and that theſe were to ſpued out of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170022:13"/>his mouth, who were of men beleeved to be good, and yet were not ſo, he premiſeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he is a teller of truth; and that in theſe things it might appear that he ought to be beleeved, therefore he cals himſelf the <hi>Amen,</hi> or <hi>that Amen,</hi> as much as to ſay, My words ſhall be found to be true, I warrant you, <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away, but one jot of my words ſhall not paſse away;</hi> When therefore you hear Jeſus Chriſt by his Spirit, in his Servants and Miniſters, threatning to ſpue you out of his mouth for your lukewarmneſſe, (for do not your conſciences tell you to your faces, that you are neither hot nor cold, nay, are many of you of any Religion at all) do not think that when your conſciences are told of theſe things Chriſt dallies with you, or that he will ſuffer himſelf to be dallied with for ever, or that it is nothing to be ſpued out of Chriſts mouth, or to take his Candleſtick from you, in caſe you think you have it; Beleeve it, eleeve it Gentlemen, If Chriſt finde you in ſuch a condition and courſe of ſinfulneſſe as to do this to you, <hi>Evemere ex ere,</hi> to ſpue you out of his mouth, I muſt be bold to tell you, that it were better for you, that you had never been born, or that ſo ſoon as you had been born, you had every one of you a milſtone tied about his neck, and that you had been caſt into the midſt of the Sea; You will finde theſe things true at the length, for he that teſtifies theſe things which I have ſpoken of, is the <hi>Amenille Amen, that Amen,</hi> not only in whom <hi>omnes promiſſiones,</hi> as one obſerveth upon the place, <hi>All the Promiſes are yea, and Amen,</hi> but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170022:14"/>from whom you will finde likewiſe <hi>Omnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minationes</hi> all the threatnings of Chriſt will be <hi>yea and Amen,</hi> to thoſe that are out of him, to thoſe that have no part nor portion in him, or whom he ſhall ſpue out of his mouth.</p>
            <p>You ſee then who it is that ſtood at the doors in my Text, 'tis Chriſt, and truly this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration might be improved a little, the better to fix upon our affections if we remember</p>
            <p n="1">1. The greatneſſe and Majeſty of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he is the party offended.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The great concernment of ſouls, that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is pleaſed to ſtand at the doore of any of us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we conſider the greatneſſe and majeſty of Chriſt, In that place of the Pſalmes which I quoted to you before, he is termed <hi>the King of glory.</hi> In the Viſion which was preſented to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John, Rev</hi> 1. you finde amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other majeſticall expreſſions, that he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed having eyes as a flaming fite, his feet were ſaid to be like fine braſſe, as if they burned in a furnace, in his right hand, he is ſaid to have the ſeven Stars, the Churches, implying, he could protect them or do with them what he would, he could throw them away if he pleaſed, <hi>Out of his mouth</hi> it is ſaid <hi>there went a ſharp two edged Sword,</hi> that could cut as faſt as it ſpoke, nay, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. Chriſt who is there called the <hi>Word of God,</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>quick and powerfull, and ſharper then any two-edged Sword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joints and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughter and intents of the hearts;</hi> My Maſters
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170022:14"/>do you think to deceive him? you will deceive your own ſouls if you think ſo, but to come to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Johns</hi> Viſion again. His Countenance is ſaid to be as the Sun ſhineth in his ſtrength: In a word his Majeſty was ſo great, ſo amazing, and ſo full of aſtoniſhment, that when S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John.</hi> ſaw him he <hi>fell at his feet as dead.</hi> His friend, his ſervant, fell down dead at the ſight of his Majeſty, what ſhall his enemies do? If the green tree be thus ſhaken, how ſhall the dry tree ſtand, when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall appear in his glorious and terrible Majeſty to judge the world in righteouſneſſe? If the righteous, if a Saint be thus terrified, What ſhall lukewarm Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites and ungodly ſinners do, when he cometh with clouds? as <hi>v.</hi> 7. tels you he will: If we go on with that verſe we ſhall fee what they will do, <hi>Behold he cometh with clouds,</hi> and what then? Then every eye ſhall ſee him, and they alſo which pierced him, as you do ſpiritually, when you deſperately ſtand out againſt his workings of loving kindeneſſe unto your ſouls, even ye which ſhut him out of doors, ſhall ſee him or feel him ſome way or other to your ſhame, to your ſorrow, for it is ſaid in the next words, <hi>and all the kindreds of the earth ſhall wail becauſe of him;</hi> All ye then that are the kindreds of the earth, whoſe hearts are ſet upon earth and earthly things, for as for the godly they are more properly the kindreds of heaven, for a like reaſon in the contrary; See what will come on you if you go on in your rebellions againſt the Lord Chriſt and his Kingdom that is now coming towards you, you will not ſea;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170022:15"/>him; you will not take notice of him now, but when he cometh with clouds, ſhall ye not ſee him then, how can ye avoid him? Ye ſhall not then only ſee him, or feel him, or both, but ye ſhall waile becauſe of him, nay and your wailing ſhall be for ever; To conclude this, If ye refuſe his mercies now, if whileſt he ſtands at your doors and knocks, ye will bid him be gone, and ſhall ſay to him as thoſe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate wicked ones in <hi>Job, Depart from us for we deſire not the knowledge of thy waies: What is the Almighty that we ſhould ſerve him? and what profit ſhould we have if we pray unto him?</hi> If we ſerve him thus, or not ſerve him at all, or bid him be gone, as I ſaid, Chriſt will pay us with a <hi>Lex talionis,</hi> he will have a <hi>Be gone</hi> for us as broad and as long as ours to him; <hi>Go ye curſed into everlaſting fire prepared for the devil and his Angels:</hi> nay, your own perſonal miſeries and Judgements will not be all, <hi>God will lay up your iniquities for your Children, be will reward you and ye ſhall know it, Job</hi> 21.19. he will reward you, nay, he will reward your children, your ſweet babes (do not your bowels earn at this?) for your wickedneſſe; What elſe can the meaning of that threarning be, <hi>He will viſit the iniquities of the Fathers upon the Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the firſt Conſideration which makes it wonderful that Chriſt ſhould thus ſtand and knock.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing in him which improves the wonder is this, that he is the party offended, My Brethren, my Brethren, we have wounded him by our tranſgreſſions, we have broken him by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170022:15"/>our ſins, and yet he is ſo willing to be friends, he longs ſo much to be reconciled, to be at one with us, that he ſtands at our doors and knocks, cals, cries, and he ſeeks entrance and reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation though he be the party offended; What a Chriſt is this? what ſinners are we? and yet it may be we think we do not ſin againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> at all, but doubtleſſe we do; when we ſinne againſt the motions of Gods Spirit, preſſing the riches of Gods goodneſſe upon us, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by it to leade us to repentance, do we not ſin againſt Chriſt? indeed ſome of us know we doe, but ſhould we do ſo ſtill? Shall we ſin againſt him, offend him for ever? What? ſo good a Chriſt ſo ill entreated? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God forbid, my Brethren, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James</hi> in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other caſe, <hi>Theſe things ought not ſo to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There is yet one Conſideration more which raiſeth the wonder, and that is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment of this rich mercy, if Jeſus Chriſt will be pleaſed to ſtand at the doores of our ſouls and knock, My Friends, do ye rightly conſider what Chriſt is doing when he is knocking at your doors? I doubt ye do not; But I will tell you, he is ſtriving to make us Kings, and Prieſts, and Prophets to our God, that with him we may reign for evermore, he is ſtriving to come in, that he may ſhew us that the Father hath forgiven us our ſins; he is ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to come in, that he may reign over our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and ſubdue our ſins to us, that he may tread Satan under our feet ſhortly, and are theſe concernments of no value with us? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it, beleeve it, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170022:16"/>may be will never knock at your doores, if you make no eſtimation of theſe things, but if you prize theſe things he will knock, he will call, yea, he will wait to be gracious, dut I beſeech you put him not to wait too long, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when he comes to you in the night, I mean in the night of your ſoul afflictions: Alas, when he comes, then remember, his <hi>head is full of dew, and his locks are filled with the drops of the night;</hi> What? ſhall we keep him out in the cold? far be it, you ſee how it concerns you to open and make him welcome, Open, Open ye poor ſouls, let him come in, he will do you no harm, yea, he will do you all good, and he will eaſe you of that burthen that troubles you moſt, that is, your ſins, why elſe doth he call you ſo eagerly ſo affectionately, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will eaſe you:</hi> Will Chriſt ſay it, and will he not do it? What will not the <hi>Amen</hi> ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to his own promiſes? ye wrong him; yea, ye do him one of the worſt of injuries to think it, to beleeve it.</p>
            <p>I have done with theſe 3 Conſiderations that render it wonderful, that Chriſt ſhould ſtand at any mans doors and knock, but I have not yet wholly done with his tranſaction of knocking.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> have a little application behinde, and if I on the behalf of Jeſus Chriſt, can make any knocking work upon your ſouls, I ſhall bleſſe my God that ever I was born, that have long been afraid that Chriſt had knockt me off for ever, becauſe being a Miniſter I have been ſo long ſilent, and held my peace, but God hath heard my praiers, and he hath had mercy on
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170022:16"/>me, even becauſe he had a favour unto me: And now I hope I ſhall ſpeak, God willing, and God I hope will help me to ſpeak to his glory and the good of your ſouls.</p>
            <p>From the Perſon then declaring himſelf, (for you ſee who 'tis,) 'tis I, 'tis I, ſaith Chriſt. Here is 1. Comfort to the drooping ſoul. 2. Terrour to the rebellious.</p>
            <p>I begin firſt with Comfort to the drooping ſoul, and indeed 'tis pity but theſe ſhould firſt be comforted, before the other be terrified, 'tis for theſe mourners ſakes amongſt others, and thoſe others that ſhall be brought to this condition, that the world ſtands, for if once the number of Gods Jewels ſhall be compleated, God will then go to gathering up of his Jewels, Jews and Gentiles together, <hi>and they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord, in the day when I make up my Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els.</hi> To you then let me firſt ſpeak, you ſee who ſtands at the door, and from whom thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Gods Spirit come, whereby your hearts are at any time wrought upon, whether terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyingly in the work of conviction upon your ſouls for ſin; by the right preaching and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Law, or comfortably by the ſweet ſtrivings and wooings of the Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Goſpel, whether at this or at other times; from whom come all theſe things? My Text tels you in effect, that they come from Chriſt, and is not Chriſt your friend think ye, why are ye afraid? O ye of little faith, yea perhaps I may as yet ſay, O ye of no faith.</p>
            <p>In the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of St. <hi>Matthewes</hi> Goſpel, we finde that Jeſus had conſtrained his Diſciples
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170022:17"/>to get into a Ship, and to goe on the other ſide of the ſea there mentioned, whileſt he ſent the multitude away: the Diſciples no doubt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that Chriſt would not be long after them, nor was he; for we finde that when the Ship was toſſed with waves in the midſt of the ſea, (for the wind was contrary) about the fourth watch of the night, Ieſus went to them walking on the ſea: The Diſciples ſeeing this were troubled, they thought they had ſeen a ſpirit, and they cried out for feare; but Chriſt quickly comforts them, <hi>Be not afraid,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>be of good checre, 'tis I.</hi> How fitly is this applicable to your ſoules, ye ſonnes and daughters of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Jeſus Chriſt hath conſtrained you to get into a Ship, a Ship of ſoul-affliction, let that be ſuppoſed to be the Ship: in this Ship ye are toſſed and tumbled with waves, for the windes are contrary, and ye think poor ſoules ye ſhall never come to your haven: ſtay, ſtay a little my ſweet daughters of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> doe not droope too much, looſe not your Anchor hold ſo eaſily; looke about you a little, and perhaps you will diſcern Chriſt walking in this ſea of your troubles. Perhaps not knowing him, when ye ſee him, nor being well acquainted with him, ye will miſtake him, and be troubled, and think 'tis a ſpirit that will deſtroy you, and that he is your enemy; 'twas thus with the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, why may it not be ſo with you? But ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>Jeſus ſtraightway spake unto them ſaying, be of good checre, it is I, be not afraid.</hi> If ye can hear Chriſt ſaying it is I, it is I, be of good chear, be not afraid, will your afflictions trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170022:17"/>you then? Waire then upon the Lord pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, you know not how ſoone Chriſt will ſhew himſelfe to you; I can aſſure you 'tis now towards the fourth watch of the night, and 'tis not long till the morning; waite comfortably under your ſtorme, your afflictions cannot laſt long, the day-ſtarre will ariſe, and if Jeſus Chriſt give you the morning-ſtarre, will it not be worth all your afflictions, all your ſorrowes, all your toſſing in theſe waters? all the troubles you have undergone in your fears? <hi>Be of good chear, 'tis I, 'tis I.</hi> Would you have more? when you hear him and ſee him, catch him in your armes, and cry out with old <hi>Simeon, The Lord now lets his Servant depart in peace, for mine eyes have ſeen his ſalvation:</hi> or as <hi>Philip</hi> which ſpake to <hi>Nathanael, I have found him of whom Moſes in the Law, and the Prophets did write, Jeſus of Nazareth, the Sonne of Joſeph,</hi> Ioh. 3.45. I have done with you at this time.</p>
            <p>I come next to the rebellious: and forgive me, if profeſſing my ſelfe a true Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, I come to you, like Chriſt, with clouds, with the clouds of Gods indignation, with clouds of darkneſſe and trouble upon your ſouls for your ſinnes, in ſuffering Chriſt to knock ſo oft, to call ſo long, to cry ſo loud, ſo that it may be truly ſaid of him, as Chriſts mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and brethren and ſiſters ſaid touching themſelves, in ſeeking Chriſt, <hi>he hath ſought you ſorrowing;</hi> and you have beene the cauſe of it, for ye have many a time ſuffered him to ſtrive, knock, call, cry, cry aloud, and yet ye have given him no entrance; he is out of doors ſtill, the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170022:18"/>door is locked ſtill; nay ye have ſet ſtrong barres of oppoſition to keep him out, nay to keep him out purpoſely. You think perhaps you have not, but I can make it apparent ye have, nay and God willing I ſhall make it appear in a ſpirituall enquiry after ſome ſoule tranſactions, before I have ended all my endeavours upon this Text. And what will ye ſay then touching your wickedneſſe? muſt ye not, will ye not ſay then, <hi>'tis of the Lords mercy we are not conſumed?</hi> how ye ſhould ſay leſſe I know not: But to prepare you herein (for this Sermon will be but the ſhell, the outſide, the kernell is to come) be pleaſed to remember from that which I have already ſpoken, that when ye ſinne againſt the motions of Gods Spirit (which I am confident hath been long ſtrugling with you,) that in ſo doing, ye ſinne likewiſe againſt Chriſt; againſt that Chriſt, that it may be hath waſhed us from our tranſgreſſions by his own bloud, and we not know it. This conſideration of ſinning againſt Chriſt, was a tender thing once with the Apoſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.12. where reproving the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for offending the conſciences of the Brethren, in eating things offered to Idols, (a thing too uſuall in a ſpirituall ſenſe in theſe daies) he reproves them, and terrifies them in ſo doing, by faſtening this upon them, that they ſinned againſt Chriſt; <hi>But when ye ſinne ſo againſt the Brethren and wound their weak Conſciences, ye ſinne againſt Chriſt;</hi> as much as to ſay: and what, will ye do that? will ye do ſo indeed? What, we Chriſtians ſinne againſt Chriſt, that hath made us ſo, that hath
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170022:18"/>waſhed us from our ſinnes by his own bloud? what we doe it! <hi>Tell it not in Gath.</hi> Let others doe it if they will, doe ye doe it if ye will, but I tell you plainely, I <hi>Paul</hi> will never doe it, God willing: <hi>wherefore, if meat make my brother to offend, I will eat no fleſh whileſt the world ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, leſt I make my brother to offend.</hi> His words by plaine and ready arguing, with halfe an eye, you may ſee to come to thus much; that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then I will ſinne againſt Chriſt (which I muſt doe if I make my brother to offend) I will not eat a bit of fleſh as long as the world laſts. Beloved, we uſe to ſay, when we are averſe to a thing, Before I will doe ſuch a thing, I will never eat bit of bread: ſuch a kinde of zeale, and ſuch a kinde of expreſſion may you imagin S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> to have been, in his reſolution of not ſinning againſt Chriſt, and yet how many are there that make no bones of this? but let them take heed, that God make not their bones and their hearts into the bargain ake for it. Sure I am, the new converts in the ſecond of the <hi>Acts,</hi> were pricked to the very heart at this very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration: ſee the place, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. You may obſerve S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter,</hi> ver. 14. beginning to preach his firſt Sermon after the aſcenſion, his firſt work is to take off a miſtake, a miſapprehenſion from the people, touching themſelves, <hi>Theſe men are not drunken, as ye ſuppoſe.</hi> At <hi>ver.</hi> 22. his Sermon begins to pinch cloſe, for he ſpeakes plainely, <hi>Ye men of Iſrael, heare theſe words, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of Nazareth, a man approved of God among you, by miracles, wonders and ſigns, which God did by him in the midſt of you, as ye your ſelves know.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170022:19"/>Ver. 23. <hi>Him being delivered by the determinate counſell and foreknowledge of God, ye have taken and by wicked hands have crucified and ſlaine.</hi> He followes this argument cloſe all along, height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſinne, by the conſideration of Gods exalting of Chriſt: and in <hi>ver.</hi> 36. he puts Gods goodneſſe to Chriſt, and their wickedneſſe againſt Chriſt both together, and with this, as with a great and irreſiſtible hammer, God pricks their hearts in <hi>Peters</hi> Miniſtry: yea he breaks them all to pieces; for ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 37. <hi>Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their hearts, and ſaid unto Peter, and to the reſt of the Apoſtles, Men and brethren what ſhall we doe?</hi> When they heard this, that the ſame Jeſus whom they had crucified, was exalted by God to be Lord and Chriſt; when they heard this, and that they had thus ſinned againſt their Lord, their Chriſt, their King; this, oh this pricked them to the quick, this ſhivered them all to pieces, this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided betwixt the joynts and marrow, it broke downe all oppoſition, <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall we doe?</hi> ſuch wretches, ſuch vile creatures as we are never were in the world. What! is that Jeſus that we have crucified, is he our Chriſt, our Lord, have we thus wronged him, thus dealt with him? <hi>Woe umo us that we have ſinned.</hi> Thus you ſee how farre this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſtrikes terror here: it did ſtrike terror into their hearts, may it not ſtrike terrour into yours? for know aſſuredly, that that ſame Jeſus, the motions of whoſe ſpirit, or of Gods Spirit, you have ſtood out againſt (I ſuppoſe you look upon it, as all one, for he and the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170022:19"/>Father are one,) is that very Jeſus, whom God hath exalted-heretofore, yea and will exalt him again, and he will make him actually both Lord and King in all the ſouls of his people, and over all the world; and this is he whom ye ſinne againſt, whom in a ſpirituall ſenſe ye crucifie againe as it were, even the Lord of glory: nay let me go further with you, and drive you up cloſer; I muſt tell you, that whileſt ye rebell againſt the workings of the Spirit of God, ye do at once ſinne againſt Father, Sonne and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, all at one ſtroake (as I may ſay:) A time bath been, and that in my dayes, when a mans naming the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt in the Pulpit, would have made many a heart to tremble; I am ſure it made mine tremble when I was a boy, and minded nothing but paſtime and pleaſure: but though I tell you (and I ſhall make it appear) that in reſiſting the motions of Gods Spirit, ye have ſinned againſt Father, Sonne and holy Ghoſt, and that your actions eſpecially in ſome, have entrenched and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered much upon the chanell of ſuch actions as do leade directly to the grand ſinne, the unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſinne, even the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, which you know Chriſt ſaith ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be pardoned in this world, nor in the world to come, yet who trembles, whoſe heart quakes? nay <hi>do we not mock at fear?</hi> and have not ſome ſucked in ſuch principles that doe ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly overturne all ſhaking, all trembling, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the apprehenſion of their ſinnes, or of Gods judgements due to them for their ſinne? My friends (for as yet I am no mans declared
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170022:20"/>enemy in the world, do not I tell you the truth? Do not your hearts and conſciences bear me witneſſe and witneſſe for me? If ſo, though you are ſo hardened that ye cannot cry out, What ſhall we do? Yet God hath ſo ſoftned my heart towards you, that I cannot but ask What ye will do? Will ye go on? I truſt in God your hearts will not let you ſay, We will go on, and we will do what ſeemeth good in our own eyes, <hi>and as for theſe words which thou hast ſpoken to us in the name of the Lord, we will not hear thee;</hi> No? will ye not? Are ye reſolved thus? if you are, I will break your reſolutions if I can, and rather then ſuffer you to runne on thus headlong into your deſtruction, I will kindle a fire in your very bones, I will vex your very ſouls, and bring you with <hi>David</hi> to cry out as he <hi>Pſa.</hi> 6. <hi>My bones are vexed O Lord yea, my ſoul is vexed, but thou O Lord how long?</hi> Conſider then in the fear of God what I aſſert, what I inſiſt upon, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he that ſinnes againſt the ſtrivings of Gods good Spirit, ſinnes againſt Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he ſins againſt the Father is evident,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From thoſe words which Chriſt uſeth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.23, 24. <hi>He that hateth me hateth my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo, If I had not done among them the works which none other man did, they had not had ſinne, but now they have both ſeen and hated both me and my Father alſo</hi> Would you have a clearer Text? He that hates the Son hates the Father, by the ſame argument. He that ſins againſt the Sonne ſins againſt the Father, and indeed he and the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170022:20"/>Father are one, or elſe Union with Chriſt would not be enough to make Chriſts poor ones one with the Father, but that this is ſufficient you may moſt remarkably ſee from that heavenly piece of Scripture, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. from <hi>v.</hi> 7. to the middle of the 11. verſe. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ye had known me, ye ſhould have known my Father alſo, and from henceforth ye know him and have ſeen him;</hi> The Diſciples ſtumbled at this, but <hi>Philip</hi> particularly ſaith to him, <hi>Lord, ſhew us the Father and it ſufficeth us;</hi> Chriſt ſeems to ſtumble at them, as much as they at him; for he ſpeaks to <hi>Philip</hi> as in their ſtead, <hi>Have I been ſo long time with you, and yet haſt thou not known me</hi> Philip? <hi>He that hath ſeen me hath ſeen the Father, and how ſaiſt thou then, Shew us the Father?</hi> Would ye have things clearer yet? <hi>viz.</hi> that Union with Chriſt is ſufficient to make up Union with the Father, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently he that ſinnes againſt Chriſt muſt needs ſinne againſt the Father; Would you I ſay have it clearer, then go on to the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>verſe, Beleevest thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me; The words that I ſpeak unto you, I ſpeak not of my ſelf;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, The Father ſpeaks them as well as <hi>I,</hi> nay, <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that dwelleth in me he doth the works too,</hi> and then he proceeds, <hi>Beleeve me</hi> (Philip) <hi>that I am in the Father and the Father in me;</hi> Plainet words then theſe ſurely cannot be uſed to aſſert the Point in hand, That ſins againſt Chriſt are ſins againſt the Father: My next work muſt be to prove that they are ſins againſt the holy Ghoſt likewiſe, and then I have done in point of proof.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170022:21"/>
            <p>To evidence this clearly and plainly, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we take it for granted, that the holy Ghoſt and the holy Spirit are all one, that being granted me as a <hi>Suppoſitum</hi> not ſo much as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by your ſelves; Let me put you in minde of ſome Texts of Scripture, wherein the ſame actions being ſpoken of, you ſhall finde are in one place implied or expreſſed plainly to be ſins againſt God, by which I underſtand to be meant the Father, in another place they are termed ſins againſt Chriſt, by which name we underſtand the Sonne, and in a third place ſins againſt Gods holy Spirit, by which 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſuppoſed we mean and underſtand the holy Ghoſt. Theſe Scriptures being produced, and aſſerting the thing in hand, I ſuppoſe I have gained the Cauſe. Compare then theſe three Scriptures together, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.10. Let us look firſt upon <hi>Num.</hi> 21.5. The people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> it ſhould ſeem were in great affliction, they wanted bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and their ſoul lothed the Manna, they call it <hi>this light bread;</hi> Being in this diſtreſſe and affliction, it is ſaid expreſly, <hi>They spake againſt God and againſt</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſaying, Wherefore have ye brought us up out of</hi> Aegypt <hi>to die in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? for there is no bread, neither is there any water, and our ſoul loatheth this light bread;</hi> here you ſee plainly the <hi>Iſraclites</hi> ſinne of murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring under this affliction, is ſaid expreſly to be againſt God, <hi>They murmured againſt God and againſt</hi> Moſes, by which word <hi>God</hi> (I hope) you will give me leave to underſtand the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and never trouble your ſelves with much
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170022:21"/>ſcruple or diſſatisfaction in the buſineſſe: Let us now go to the next Scripture which ye ſhall finde, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.9. <hi>Neither let us tempt Chriſt, as ſome of them alſo tempted, and were deſtroied of Serpents;</hi> The Queſtion will be, how it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the ſame ſin is ſpoken of in both places; To make this ſure, I muſt turn you back to <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.6. again, which tels us that God for their ſin of murmuring immediatly before, ſent fiery Serpents among the people, and they died; Now reade the verſe I have quoted out of the <hi>Corinthians, Neither let us tempt Chriſt as ſome of them alſo tempted, and were deſtroied of Serpents,</hi> Do you deſire I ſhould argue now? Is it not plain that that which was called murmuring againſt God in the Book of <hi>Numbers</hi> is called <hi>tempting of Chriſt</hi> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians?</hi> For what did the Lord ſend fiery Serpents among the people? <hi>for murmuring againſt God:</hi> For what were they deſtroied of Serpents? <hi>for tempting of Chriſt:</hi> Theſe then were both one, unleſſe you underſtand any other deſtruction of Serpents to be intended by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> then this which was by the biting of the fiery Serpents, mentioned in the Book of <hi>Numbers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My proofs touching Father and Sonne I have done with, My next labour muſt be touching the holy Spirit or holy Ghoſt as we call him; For this view my third Text, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.10. where the Prophet having in the verſe before mentioned the gracious and generall loving kindeneſſe of the Lord toward his people in the daies of old, ſets down in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170022:22"/>next words in the beginning of the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, the general demeanour and carriage of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> his people toward God; And what was their carriage? 'Twas ſad I confeſſe, I fear ours is ſo too, <hi>They rebelled and vexed his holy Spirit;</hi> Their general poſture of actions againſt God is termed here you ſee <hi>a rebelling and vexing his holy Spirit,</hi> certainly if all their wicked actions come under this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; then this action likewiſe of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring againſt God, or tempting of Chriſt being one of their actions, muſt needs do ſo too. And now I think I have gained my cauſe.</p>
            <p>Having done with my proof, let me now treat with you a little, you that have ſin'd ſo often againſt the motions of Gods Spirit, and therein in ſome ſenſe troden under foot the Son of God, for Gods ſake, What do ye think of your ſelves? have ye done well, think ye, thus at one blow (as it were) to ſtrike Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt in the face? Is this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for his mercies in ſending Jeſus Chriſt to ſhed his bloud for your ſins, a fair recompence to the Father? Is it equal that ſuch a <hi>Lex Talionis</hi> ſhould be returned to the Son, that we ſhould thus grieve and vex the holy Spirit? Certainly if there be any fear of God before out eyes, the doing of theſe things cannot rightly pleaſe our hearts: But becauſe ye are ſo hardened in your wickedneſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions againſt him, who will either glorifie you, if ye willingly ſubmit to him, or torment you for ever, if ſtill ye perſiſt, be ye under what
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170022:22"/>Form or Adminiſtrations ye will; For I love not to flatter you in your imaginary ſhadow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taken up of your own heads, nor do I place godlineſſe or wickedneſſe in externall Forms, but rather in ſubmitting or walking contrary to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Let me preſſe you a little eagerly to conſider what ye are doing, when ye are ſinning againſt the motions, workings, and pleadings of Gods good Spirit, ſtriving within you, as doubtleſſe ſometimes he doth, or elſe things go very ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with you; Be as merry as ye will; Shall I minde you in one word what ye do? ye ſinne againſt Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt all at once, ye do in a ſenſe (as I told you) tread under foot the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, for this treading things under foot what is it? 'tis an expreſſion, whereby we ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie our ſcorning and lothing of a thing, as when we ſay, If I could, I would tread thee under my foot, My Brethren, my brethren, what do ye leſſe when ye do ſo reſiſt the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods good Spirit, that ye cannot endure to hear him ſpeak to you? Nay, how many are there, who when the Spirit of God would pleade with them, and reaſon them into god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, or into the omiſſion of this, or that, or the other particular ſin, as of whoredom, jeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at good things, drunkenneſſe, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, or the like, preſently they take the firſt occaſion they can of ſetting themſelves againſt their own mercies, they cannot endure the Lord to ſpeak as it were one word more: And therefore choaking him as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170022:23"/>ſoon as they can, they run preſently into a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge of lies, good fellowſhip, drinking, muſick, ſome paſtime or other to ſtop the mouth of conſcience which would be convincing them of ſinne, of righteouſneſſe, of judgement to come, and by arguments drawn from thence would ſtagger them at their ſinful courſes, but none of that I thank you, their ſins and they cannot part company ſo eaſily, and therefore the Spirit of God is looked upon by them as their enemy, becauſe it tels them the truth, and will not flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, nor ſuffer them to run ſo quietly to their own deſtruction; With ſome perhaps he gets a little faiter quarter, they will hear the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, conſider the terrors of Gods judgements which are threatned ſpiritually to their inward man, to reclaim them from their ſins, but when they have heard all, they think to make up all with a little humiliation, a few tears, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle rugging and ſtriving to cry to God for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and if upon a duty of praier or humiliation they finde a little peace and quietneſſe, though Gods intention in giving it, be but barely to bear up their hearts under ſoul affliction, untill the times of a more full and more gracious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation comes, then up they get upon their tiptoes preſently, their afflictions are all vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or baniſhed in a moment; God is their God now ſure, <hi>for</hi> (ſay they) <hi>he hath heard our ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he hath forgiven our ſinnes;</hi> herein miſerably miſtaking a little arbitrary conſolation, which God grants in a deſigne of ſupporting the ſoul, till it be fit for a more gracious diſpenſation, for a ſure ſignification of forgiveneſſe of ſins; the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170022:23"/>groſleneſſe of which miſtake, I ſhall clear upon ſome occaſion or other, in Gods good time, and it may be before I have ended my meditations upon this Text.</p>
            <p>Some the Spirit of God prevails ſo farre with, that</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are willing to be reproved and chid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for their ſins, but from thence are too apt to conclude a ſure eſtate of ſoul.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The work of conviction being ſtrong upon their ſouls, they are apt to make many fair pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, many ſtrong engagements, that they will do ſo no more.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But then thirdly, when Gods back is but turned (as I may ſay,) or that they think him but out of ſight, they ſtart aſide like a broken bow, and neither promiſes, Covenants, or any other obligations prevail with them at all, but they turn <hi>with the dog to their own vomit, and with the ſow to the wallowing in the mire;</hi> and if the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Gods Spirit preſſe them to conſider their breach of vowes and Covenants, and their promiſes of better obedience, they either heal their hurt ſlightly, with a few prayers and teares, and then they think all is well, as I obſerved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: or ſecondly by a long practiſe of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly eourſes they come at length to ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate hardneſſe of heart, that they conclude there is no hope, and ſo conceive it to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſtrive any more, to pray any more, to be humbled any more, to hearken to the motions of Gods Spirit any more: the finall concluſion is, as they throw off all hope, ſo they throw off all duty, and let Chriſt by his Spirit ſay what he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170022:24"/>will, they think all is to no purpoſe, to hear him or obey him; and this laſt and worſt part of this character, hath been my own caſe for almoſt this nine years or thereabouts, till within this year and a half; about which time, apprehending ſome abatement of thoſe judgements, which my apprehenſions had been long terrified with, for my grievous ſins, eſpecially for hiding my little Talent, which I looked upon as given me by God, not to hide, but to publiſh: I was about a year and half ſince, reſolved to ſubmit my ſelf to be at Gods diſpoſing, and to ſerve God as well as I could, though I looked for nothing but hell as my portion for ever, only I hoped it would be hell mitigated, and me thought I had ſtrange kinde of hopes, that in hell I ſhould finde a little comfort, and a little ſtrength to endure it, and to dwell with everlaſting burnings, becauſe I was willing to ſubmit; but theſe ſtrange hopes ſoon vaniſhed and became nothing: for about a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or half a year after, I was thrown down again into the dreadfulleſt apprehenſions of Gods eternall judgements, that ever were preſented to any mortall man upon Gods earth, ſince the creation of God, or that the world began: with this heavy load of apprehenſions I walked for above half a year together, <hi>viz.</hi> all this laſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and ſome little part of the beginning of winter; but at length the ſpring is come, and the chirping of Birds hath been heard by me, there was never ſuch mercy ſhewed, ſuch compaſſion manifeſted to any ſoul in the world; I am alive, and the loving kindneſſe of God hath appeared to me: But I tell you, my brethren and friends,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170022:24"/>my rebellion againſt Jeſus Chriſt, my ſtanding out againſt the motions of Gods good Spirit, hath coſt me dear, and ſo dear, I would not for a hundred thouſand worlds endure the like hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors again: It would amaze you all, nay almoſt affright you out of your wits, to tell you what I have ſeen, but God in Jeſus Chriſt I truſt hath delivered me for ever; and God ſtrengthning me, I will praiſe him for it, yea I will magnifie him as long as I have my being.</p>
            <p>And now my dear friends, I am ſet forth to you as an example of Gods terrors and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if ye ſhall rebell againſt Chriſt, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually reſiſt the motions of Gods gracious Spirit ſtriving with you as I have done: I am withall a mirrour of Gods infinite rich mercies, in the pardoning of iniquities, and an example of heartning to you, if God ſhall be pleaſed to give you repentance from your ſins and from all your ungodly courſes, as to me I hope in God he hath done in ſome meaſure: but if having ſuch a warning given, in ſuch grievous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if the riches of Chriſts mercies in finding a way to pardon ſuch a ſinner as I am, if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe, nor both together prevaile with you, nor be a means to hearten you, and to cauſe you to live in ſome hope, at leaſt, that it may be the Lord will have ſome mercy, ſome compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for you as well as for me: If I ſay, theſethings will be no means to reclaim you, then I muſt be bold to tell you, that I cannot ſay ſo much as a Judge to a condemned perſon, Lord have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon your ſouls, I muſt leave you to God; only at preſent let me put you in minde of theſe things which follow,</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170022:25"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That it is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God,</hi> Heb. 10.31. <hi>for our God is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire,</hi> Heb. 12.29.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That certainly you have ſucked in ſome deſperate principles touching the decree and election of God, which do ſo poiſon your ſouls with hopeleſneſſe, that, if ye come to hear a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, 'tis for very ſhame of the world, leſt men ſhould account you of no religion, accounting it in all other reſpects vain and unprofitable, either to hear a Sermon or to ſerve God at all; and the truth is, I much ſuſpect this latter, it having had a ſtrong influence into my own troubleſome and dreadfull apprehenſions for ſo long together.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That you will finde it dangerous indeed, to dally with Jeſus Chriſt a little longer; he is now coming in a ſolemne manner, to treat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the buſineſſe of leaving of our ſinnes and turning to God, and this I hope to evidence clearly, as occaſion ſhall offer it ſelf, if I can have the liberty of a publike Pulpit as I deſire; but if I cannot, I truſt Jeſus Chriſt who is now nigh at hand in his ſpiritual coming, will vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate me from the charge of being guilty of other mens tranſgreſſions, which (God willing) I will endeavour to my utmoſt to prevent (if I may be ſuffered,) but if I alone muſt be hindred, I hope God will regard my innocency, and men will at length know my integrity and affection to their ſouls.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170022:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
